Women's International Democratic Federation Records, 1945-1979
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Women's International Democratic Federation records
1945-1979
Women's International Democratic Federation
MS 594
4 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Pacifist organization, Peace activists. Records contain printed materials dating from the founding in 1946 to its investigation by HUAC in 1949; publications of international affiliates; and records of congresses sponsored by WIDF between 1945 and 1969, primarily from the World Congress of Women held in Helsinki in 1969. Included is a biography of the founder Eugenie Cotton; correspondence of the Congress of American Women (American affiliate); and materials relating to the Vietnam War and International Women's Day.
Historical Note
The Women's International Democratic Federation (WIDF) was founded in Paris in 1945 at the International Congress of Women by Eugenie Cotton and Marie-Claude Vaillant-Courturier. It was organized around four major concerns: anti-fascism, international peace, child welfare, and the status of women. In a 1958 interview Eugenie Cotton stated, "It was Fascism that caused the 1939-1945 war and because of this the founders of WIDF stressed their determination to work for the strengthening of democracy in the world. When they demand peace, women think first and foremost of safeguarding the lives of their children." ["Madame Cotton Tells Us"] There were Communists active in the organization and as a result, the American press labeled it as "Communist dominated."
The American affiliate of the WIDF, the Congress of American Women (CAW), was founded in New York City in 1946 to "revive the struggles of the nineteenth century woman's movement and attract women radicalized by their wartime experiences into the larger progressive movement" [Weigand 47] Shortly thereafter CAW established itself as an American branch of the WIDF. In response to the House Un-American Activities Committee's (HUAC) charge that the WIDF was a tool of the Soviet Union, the CAW disaffiliated from the WIDF in December 1949 and voted to disband in 1950.
The WIDF is an ongoing organization. According to its website it has affiliates in 160 countries.
Works Cited
Women of the Whole World, "Madame Cotton Tells Us." April 1958.
Weigand, Kate, Red Feminism: American Communism and the Making of Women's Liberation.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The WIDF records are divided into four Series as follows:
I. GENERAL consists of miscellaneous statements, appeals, messages, subscription information, and WIDF's Tenth Anniversary publication (1955).
II. AFFILIATES contains general information, publications, and clippings about WIDF affiliates in China, Hungary, Romania, and Yugoslavia as well as correspondence mostly with Zelma Brandt, co-chairman of the Committee of International Affairs, clippings, reports, and publications of the U.S. affiliate, the Congress of American Women (CAW). CAW materials date from the founding of the organization in 1946 to its investigation by HUAC in 1949.
II. CONGRESSES consists of records of seven congresses sponsored by WIDF between 1945 and 1969. The bulk of this series consists of agenda, financial reports, timetables, reports, speeches and anti-Vietnam War material from the World Congress of Women held in Helsinki in 1969.
III. PUBLICATIONS contains WIDF publications including Eugenie Cotton, a biography of the founder of the WIDF, Documents and Information, News In Brief and Vietnam. Also included are miscellaneous pamphlets and printed material. The WIDF's magazine, Women of the Whole World (1951-91), can be found in the SSC's periodicals collection.
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Zelma Brandt, co-chairman of the Committee of International Affairs, Congress of American Women, donated her records of the WIDF and CAW between 1968 and 1972.
International Women's Day--History; Socialism--History--20th century--Sources; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Protest movements--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--20th century--Sources; Women socialists; Women's rights--Congresses--History--Sources; Women communists; World Congress of Women (1969: Helinski, Finland); Brandt, Zelma Corning; Congress of American Women--History--Sources; Women's International Democratic Federation--History--Sources
Additional WIDF materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the papers of Mary Metlay Kaufman, Dorothy Kenyon, Mary van Kleeck, and Ruth Frances Woodsmall. WIDF's magazine Women of the Whole World is located with the Periodicals Collection.
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  - General, 1954-75, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tenth anniversary publication, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. AFFILIATES
  - Lists, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Central Committee of the Women's Anti-Fascist Front of Yugoslavia: Bulletin, 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Congress of American Women (Box 1)
    - General, 1946-49, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1946-48, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Publications, 1946-48, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hungarian Women's Council, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - National Women's Federation of the People's Republic of China, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Women's National Council of the Socialist Republic of Romania, 1966, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. CONGRESSES
  - Women's International Congress, Paris, 1945 (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Account of the Work (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
  - Women's International Congress (2nd), Budapest, 1948 (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Account of the Work" (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - World Congress of Women, Copenhagen, 1953 (Box 1)
    - General (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Preparation (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Reports, Speeches, Documents" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Special Information Bulletin After the World Congress of Women," 1953-54 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - World Congress of Mothers, Lausanne, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fourth Congress of WIDF, Vienna, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - World Gathering of Women for Disarmament, Vienna, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7a)
  - World Congress of Women, Moscow, 1963 (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Information Bulletin" (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - World Congress of Women, Helsinki, 1969 (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Report on Activities of the WIDF" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "La Cause Palestienne et la Legitimite de la Resistance" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Women at Work" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Women in Society" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Women in the Family" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Women in the Struggle to Win and Defend National Independence, Democracy and Peace" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Speeches (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Vietnam War: reports, draft appeal, and declarations (Box 2, Folder 18)
- SERIES IV. PUBLICATIONS
  - General (Box 2)
    - 1950s-60s (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Documents and Information (Box 3)
    - 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 2-14)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Eugenie Cotton, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Information Bulletin, 1948-50 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - International Women's Day messages, 1958-75 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - News In Brief, 1953-57, 1968-73, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
  - Vietnam, 1972-74 (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
  - Women of the Whole World, 1951-91 [see Periodicals collection] (Box 4)